<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Robert Rich his second letters from Barbadoes writ upon the occasion of the Quakers prevarication in the matter of the 30 l. sent to them in common with their brethren the other six churches so termed by him. With a preface extorted from R.B. phil. to the said people.</title>
            <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220588</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831984</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831984</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2132:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Robert Rich his second letters from Barbadoes writ upon the occasion of the Quakers prevarication in the matter of the 30 l. sent to them in common with their brethren the other six churches so termed by him. With a preface extorted from R.B. phil. to the said people.</title>
                  <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
                  <author>R. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18 [i.e. 28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year MDCLXIX. [1669]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To my beloved friends separate from their brethren by the name of Quakers, .." signed: R.B. Phil.</note>
                  <note>Page 28 is misnumbered 18.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36451:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36451:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. Robert Rich His Second LETTERS FROM <hi>BARBADOES;</hi> Writ upon the occaſion of The QUAKERS Prevarication In the matter of the 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> ſent to them in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with their Brethren the other ſix Churches ſo termed by him.</p>
            <p>With a PREFACE Extorted from <hi>R. B. Phil.</hi> to the ſaid People.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Open rebuke is better then ſecret love.</hi> 
               <bibl>Prov.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Rebuke a wiſe man, and he will love thee.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for the Author, in the Year MDCLXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:36451:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36451:2"/>
            <head>To my beloved friends ſeparate from their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by the name of <hi>Quakers, R. E. Ph.</hi> wiſheth better information, more humility, <hi>e</hi> love, together with a renewed renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of themſelves in the will of God.</head>
            <p>THeſe enſuing Letters of Mr. <hi>Robert Rich,</hi> though they have been long in my hands, yet they have at length come forth to publick view, more through your default, then my either endeavour or deſire. I have waited long, and hoped much, that at length you would have come to a conſideration of your miſcarriage in this matter, and made ſome acknowledgement to God, Mr. <hi>Rich,</hi> and indeed to me, whom you know unanimous with him in this laſt, and onely ſaving diſpenſation of divine love and grace exhibited by and through him irreſpectively to all. But you above all, have not onely rejected it, but blaſphemed, and ſpoken evil of it and him: ſhewing your ſelves herein, <hi>contrary unto all men,</hi> as the Apostle ſomewhere ſpeaks of the perverſe and obſtinate Jews, who rejected Jeſus the common Saviour of all men that believe in him. Your ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ff rings indeed in the outward have been great, and you have hitherto, as it were in your own belief, born away the Bell, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed greatly over all others: but the hour of your judgement is alſo now come, even as you have feared (to my knowledge) it would alſo come upon you For what meant elſe your unchristian and violent withſtanding and rejecting that appearance of God in <hi>J. N. J P.</hi> and many others, and now last of all in Mr. <hi>Rich,</hi> who have dug and opened a well among you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you have in your pride re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed to drink of, <hi>viz</hi> another and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſpenſation: the dread of which hath been long upon you; and that for this onely cauſe, becauſe it is open to others, you the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, in equality to your ſelves. What is this, but that of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnation, that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k it ill at his fathers hands, that a prodigal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:36451:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>had waſted all he had upon harlots, found upon his return better favour then he did, that never offended him? This was the ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-block of old, that the worst of ſinners, as <hi>Mary Magdalene, Zacheus,</hi> and <hi>Matthew</hi> the Publican, became diſciples of Jeſus, when they that judged themſelves the light of the world, and the onely men to be ſaved (as the Phariſees) ſtumbled and fell. I had thought to have given you herein the hiſtory of your whole and beſt attainment, where you begun, when you fell, and what will in God undoubtedly be the <hi>exit</hi> of you, to wit, the ſame that hath betide others, that boasted as much as you: for you have but (as you think) run in a ſtraight line, but ſtill in the ſame path, whoſe glory was, and yours is, the abhorrencie of certain outward forms and ceremonies introduced of old by wiſer men then your ſelves, to wit, the Elders or Teachers of the people, for a manuduction to the holy underſtanding of the heavenly things themſelves, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and whereby Chriſtianity was upheld in great unity and glory for many hundreds of years, till there was a ſtrife about them, (among which contenders I am exceedingly afflicted that you are alſo as out of due time found) all tending nothing or very little to amendment; yea, the matter was and is made worſe thereby: for from thence came wars and horrible murders, perſecutions, and devaſtations, and that on either hand. Wherefore God from on high hath, as heretofore, ſo at this preſent, out of infinite grace and mercy re-viſited the earth with his love, (<hi>i.e.</hi> himſelf) invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all (by his ſent-Miniſters) to beat their ſwords into plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhares, and their ſpears into pruning-books; that at length the earth may be redeemed from under the curſe, and bring forth no more ſuch briers and thorns, but fruit to the glory of God, and the ſalvation of men univerſal, which is manifeſt in the love which is of God, and is God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Extorted from your true friend and obſerver, R.B. <hi>Phil</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36451:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. <hi>John Raynes,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have lately received from you two Letters, dated the 3 of <hi>February,</hi> and 23 <hi>March,</hi> with Receipts under the hands of thoſe who received from you the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> and that have undertook to diſtribute the ſame to the Poor amongſt them. Alſo, I take notice of the care and pains taken by your ſelf, and the reſt of my friends, Mr. <hi>Blackbury,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rallinſon,</hi> whom you write have much aſſiſted you in this Service of Love; to whom I return my moſt hearty thanks, and hope to finde ſuch an opportunity, as I may make you ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acknowledgement then by words onely. In truth I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended you not altogether ſo much trouble as I ſee you have put your ſelves (and others) unto, in asking and taking Receipts from them. I onely deſired to know the names of thoſe to whom you gave the money, that ſo I might have the fairer opportunity to ſend them what in writing I have already prepared. Yet when I conſider what hath ſince happened between me and the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> I am glad, for the Truths ſake, that you ſent me their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt.</p>
            <p>In yours of the 23 of <hi>March,</hi> I underſtand that the large Letter I writ to you is put into Print, and do believe what you writ concerning the ſame, how that you had no hand in printing of it, and that it was printed without your conſent, aſſent, or knowledge. And you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſure, can bear me witneſs, that I did never in the leaſt intimate any ſuch thing to you, (as the Lord knows I never did to any one elſe) nor was it ever the intent of my heart, that ſuch a fooliſh private Letter ſhould have come abroad to the publike view of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> that envious, ſcoffing, mocking generation, whoſe work it is to pervert and miſconſtrue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36451:4"/>all that others ſay and do, though never ſo innocent. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> foreſaw what is come to paſs, how that a publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof would expoſe me (both by Profeſſors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane) to much reproach and ſcorn: yet I have been by none ſo ſhamefully vilified and abuſed, as by the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who publikely accuſed me for putting that my Letter in print, and ſaid I had thereby blown a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. To the truth of which I appeal to all men, that if I have intimated the printing thereof to any one (my deſire is) that ſuch a one would publiſh me to be a baſe deceitful l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing perſon, and that the truth is not found in me; or if the <hi>Quakers</hi> have herein falſly accuſed me, that the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent may henceforth go free, and the guilty bear their own ſhame. And as to their accuſation of calling <hi>Giles Calvert</hi>'s wife Whore in that Letter; I ſuppoſe every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Reader, free from prejudice, (and the Letter the ſame printed which I writ; for as yet I have not ſeen the printed one) will ſoon ſee that I intended her no evil in what I writ concerning her husband, whom I compared to <hi>Rahab the harlot,</hi> for that likewiſe he did readily, with much hazard and danger, receive, hide, and publiſh the ſpiers out of Truth and new Light. And I farther declare to all, how that I never ſaw nor knew worſe or more evil by Mris <hi>Calvert,</hi> then by a childe that is newly born into the world. To the truth of which, I ſay (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>Behold, before God I lye not:</hi> which oath, aſſeveration, or proteſtation, I hope will perſwade all rational men and women, that I intended her no evil in what I writ, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther love and kindneſs to him and his, whom though dead and abſent in body, yet I remember (the ſpirit and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that ſo acted him) with much reſpect and loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing that Letter I writ to you in private is made publike, I have thus much to ſignifie to the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as I have to all others that wonder at and deſpiſe the ſame, That it is to them a call out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> inviting them and intreating them to forſake the Garlick and Onions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, even all thoſe dark paths of enmity, falſhood, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36451:4"/>that they would forbear any longer to give the Innocent of their wormwood and gall to drink: rather, let them ſtudie peace and quietneſs, and learn to love their enemies, yea if poſſible turn (that which ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) evil into good, or at the leaſt reward evil with that which is good, and not pervert the words and actions of others (which are honeſtly and innocently intended) to an evil and wrong ſenſe. And I dare aſſure them, that to follow this way and ſpirit of harmleſs love and kindneſs will ſooner bring them into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> viz. into peace and reſt with that of God in all his creation, then their high talk of infallibility and ſelf-perfect on ſhall do, or their ſaying (with the Phariſees of old) that God is their father, whilſt they are doing the devils work, and ſound ſmiting, tearing and devouring the innocent, their fellow-ſervants. Aſſuredly, theſe their high notions and lofty imaginations will no longer ſerve to hide them from the wrath of the Lamb, who is now ariſing to take vengeance of all that have had a hand in ſlaying him; for a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is making between the pretions and the vile, between him that ſerveth God in newneſs of heart, in the upright ſpirit of love in well doing, and thoſe that ſerve and pleaſe themſelves, a Sect, a Party, or an Opinion onely. And were not perſecutors blinde in heart, and hardened, they would ſoon diſcern, how that love that thinks none ill, gives no evil wrathful names, (eſpecially to thoſe they knew no evil by) as <hi>Ranters, Whoremongers, Devils,</hi> &amp;c. And that this is not the ſpirit of the Lamb, but the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon that caſts out his flouds of enmity after the man-child (the ſon of love) who ſurely muſt and will take the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and get the victory over enmity, the worſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemy of mankinde.</p>
            <p>I alſo give you to underſtand, that lately I have received a Letter from Mr. <hi>Rallinſon,</hi> and one from Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I perceive there is ſomewhat of diſagreement concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſpoſe of the thirty pounds to the ſeventh Church of the firſt-born. For my own particular, I call God for a witneſs upon my ſoul, that I intended nothing in my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36451:5"/>heart which might make the leaſt diviſion amongſt the people of God therein; it being a work which in truth tended in it ſelf to the gathering and uniting of all the ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi> (diſperſed and ſcattered amongſt the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſtitutions of all outward Forms) into the <hi>new Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> viz. the free grace and love of God, which appears to all men, and comes down out of heaven adorned as a bride, to woo and win the ſouls and ſpirits of men to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain and embrace him who was, now is, and for ever the univerſal ſpirit of Love and Right Reaſon, the true <hi>Elixir</hi> and Philoſophers Stone, that which turns all into its ſelf, cements, unites, and reconciles all the people of God into one principle of love, (the original centre of all peace and order) though (in names) never ſo much divided in the vaſt circumference of all worldly and carnal Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>However, I know, and have long ſeen, that offences muſt and will be, and that the wo is to them who are offended with what is juſt and innocent. For <hi>ſurely this is the day of Jacobs troubles,</hi> wherein <hi>for the diviſion of Reuben</hi> (the firſt birth, which ſtands in uniformity to man in the things of God) <hi>there will be great thoughts of heart.</hi> Inſomuch that if any offence ariſe in this particular, (the Lord knowing my innocencie therein) makes me to ſay, <hi>Bleſſed are ye that are not offended in me,</hi> or rather in what the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.31. &amp; 13.47. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.38 &amp; 39. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.14, &amp;c. <hi>H ſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 32. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſpirit of love worketh in man: for I ſee the Spirits leading is that ſtone and rock of offence, at which many in <hi>Iſrael</hi> have ſtumbled, and (falling headlong as <hi>Judas</hi> did, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.18.) are burſt aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and all their bowels of love are guſhed out, and nought left them, ſave wrath and enmity againſt the innocent brethren. This ſpurning and ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at the Corner-ſtone, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Gods Spirit and Son in man, is the onely ground of all theſe breakings and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which at this day are amongſt all ſorts of profeſſors: yea, the ſon and heir of heaven, the light and truth in the inward parts, is become the gin and ſnare to <hi>Iſrael</hi> after
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36451:5"/>the fleſh, who<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5.</note> think they do God good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, when they ſmite, backbite and devour the innocent and upright in heart (as if to follow other mens light would ſave the ſoul, rather then to follow the light of true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and meaſure of God in themſelves; or as if any thing acted and done without the power of the Spirits leading (in things ſpiritual) were acceptable to God the Father.) Now the true cauſe of all that diviſion, ſtrife and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (in matters of Religion over all Chriſtendom) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in this, that every man or Sect (who is not born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain of the immortal ſeed of Love) hath a way and work of their own,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.12. &amp; 5 43. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 18. &amp; 10.3, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.10</note> contrary to Chriſt Jeſus, and the leadings of his Spirit; the maintenance of which cauſeth all that enmity and perſecution amongſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Chriſtianity: for whilſt man abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the light, law and love of God writ in the heart, the new and living way, he groweth up into the ſame i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and likeneſs, and is filled with that humility, joy, and charity, which worketh nor thinketh any evil of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: but when man leaves and forſakes Gods grace in himſelf, (the which is ſufficient to lead into the love of all truth) and by his own induſtry partakes of the ſtoln wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the harlot, <hi>(viz.)</hi> mans inventions and teachings in things ſpiritual; he will then with all the bitterneſs and violence of man, endeavour to defend this Idol, (read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.12.) as more affecting the work of his own hands, then reſpecting the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33 &amp; 34 <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. <hi>Mic</hi> 6.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. &amp; 16. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.5. to 11. &amp; 4.7. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.63.</note> Rule which God hath given him to walk by. And hence it is that one ſaith <hi>I am of Paul, another of Apollo, and a third of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> or of Chriſt after the fleſh; or after this or that mans opinion or interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the letter of the Scripture; as if Chriſtianity ſtood in the names and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of men, and not in the power of the new birth and ſpirit that was in Chriſt Jeſus. Read <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36451:6"/>8.9, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Behold, thus do National Churches and ſpiritleſs profeſſors gather together into outward, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, carnal aſſemblies, heaping up to themſelves Doctors and Teachers, the beſt of whom are but Briers, and the moſt upright among them but as a thorn-hedge, whoſe proper work is to vilifie others, to rend, tear, and devour all who (in the naked ſimplicity of their hearts) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to follow the Lord, that ſpirit of Love, as their onely Shepherd, Guide and Leader.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe the Lord is coming out of his place, to puniſh the earthly inhabitants of all formal Religion; and will ſurely divide the ſpoil with the ſtrong, and ſcatter the proud perſecutors in their own imaginations. And becauſe he hath made his grave with the wicked, and his witneſſes for truth and righteouſneſs have been long trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under foot, and numbred amongſt tranſgreſſors, (have been ſmitten and ſlain) not onely at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and ſelf-righteous, but have been alſo crucified by the profane in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt.</hi> Read <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he now ariſing to daſh the potſherds of the earth one againſt another, brother againſt brother, one againſt two, and two againſt three, till the earth have diſcloſed the bloud ſhe hath drunk, and the ſeed of God be recovered, (out of that reproach and ſhame under which it hath layn buried by the inveterate and implacable ſpirit of a carnal formal Profeſſion) yea, redeemed to walk in Gods way, which he by his Spirit ſhall direct in every heart and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. For this I know and do declare, that my God will not leave overturning, overturning, overturning, till he comes who brings along with him truth and love to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and righteouſneſs, whoſe right it is thus to rule and reign in the hearts and conſciences of his people, whoſe way ſhall be proſperous upon the earth, and unto whom is given <hi>the heathen for his inheritance, and the uttermost parts of the earth for his poſseſsion:</hi> he will <hi>ſave his people from their ſins, and guide their feet into the way of truth, peace and rest. Selah.</hi> Behold the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. <hi>Jo.</hi> 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Lamb of God, and King of Saints. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36451:6"/>Now whilſt theſe veſſels of wrath are pouring out, and this diſpenſation of vengeance laſteth, I do not intend to ſend what I have written to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom,</hi> but rather ſhall wait the Fathers pleaſure, which I account the full meaſure of time, and fitteſt ſeaſon for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very purpoſe. And becauſe I ſee the Son of (God in) man is coming forth to bruiſe (as with a rod of Iron) the unrighteous Nations, not to bring peace, but a ſword; I alſo, in obedience to the Fathers commands, have ſold my Coat, (made of good-will to all, both perſons and things) that I might purchaſe a Sword, with which (contrary to my nature) I am conſtrained to plead like a man of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, againſt this proud, Phariſaical and perverſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, this <hi>Leviathan</hi> and crooked Serpent, in whoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils unleſs a hook be put, would ſwallow not onely the Rivers, but alſo the very Sea into himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> receive all, (though never ſo unclean in heart and ſpirit) if outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will but own him, receive his mark, and number of his name, (that is the chief in every Sect) and walk in outward obſervation and ſhew conformable to them; who whilſt they profeſs themſelves free from ſin, and boaſt of having <hi>Abraham</hi> to their father, and being the only chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, are notwithſtanding found bitter perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the truth, and enemies to the Unction, the Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted One, in whomſoever he doth appear; thereby ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring themſelves guilty of all that innocent bloud which hath been ſpilt, from the bloud of righteous <hi>Abel</hi> even unto this day; all which bloud cryeth aloud for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon the welfavoured harlot, <hi>(Myſtery Babylon)</hi> who in the golded cupe, and goodly ſhew of an outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, hath inwardly (with a bitter ravening devouring ſpirit) made her ſelf drunk with the bloud of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus. Even ſo, Lord God Almighty (as ſhe hath done) give her bloud to drink, for ſhe is worthy. <hi>Amen. Hallelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what concerns the diſtribution of the thirty pounds to the ſeventh Church, (if not already diſpoſed of) my friend Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> hath remembred me of a way (formerly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36451:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the intent of my heart) which I hope will pleaſe you all, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to give that money to thoſe, who belong not to any of the firſt ſix Congregations, but to ſuch as are redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the evil of all Sects, Kindreds, Nations, Tongues, and People; who have no viſible Church or people to ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter under; who have trodden the wine-preſs of Gods wrath alone, and patiently ſuffered much evil for their work of well-doing; who worſhip God in the ſincere ſpirit of love to truth and righteouſneſs, and can call no man Father nor Maſter of their faith, light and ſpirit, neither own any man their Miniſter or Teacher, ſave the Spirit of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (the Chriſt of God) onely; who have the Fathers<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34 &amp; 35. <hi>Mat</hi> 5.44, &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.35.</note> mark in their forehead, can own all that fear God and love righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, amongſt Jews or Gentiles, Barbarians or Scychians, under any Sect or ſort of people whatſoever. To theſe, and ſuch as theſe, I deſire Mr. <hi>Blackbury,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rallinſon</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> to diſtribute that money in their hands.</p>
            <p>Alſo, to this Tribe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> I give a double portion; this, and that likewiſe which is promiſed to be returned me from the <hi>Quakers:</hi> which laſt thirty pounds when recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I deſire may alſo be diſpoſed of by Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Blackbury,</hi> according to a Liſt here encloſed, the which contains (as I am informed) the names of ſome few outcaſts from amongſt the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> whom I dearly ſalute and own (as my brother <hi>Benjamin</hi>) bone of my bone, and fleſh of my fleſh, whoſe body is not carnal, but (mighty through grace to the pulling down of ſin and wickedneſs in themſelves) like unto his glorious body; whoſe members are made of love to enemies; living ſtones, elect and precious; (though rejected by men of all Sects, yet) theſe are the true Church of God, and Citie of our King, who dwelleth, ruleth, and reigneth in them. <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee, my dear friend and friends, that in ſtead of coming out of your debt, I ſtill run farther therein: which debt (in the day of recompence which is not afar off) my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36451:7"/>God I hope will repay you manifold into your boſomes, even in this life, and in the world to come peace and reſt with us, even that peace which this world can neither give nor take away, <hi>(viz.)</hi> life eternal, which is in the Son of Gods free grace and love ſhed abroad in our hearts: a kingdom which remaineth to all the heirs of ſalvation, from everlaſting to everlaſting. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus with my dear and hearty kinde reſpects to your ſelf, Mr. <hi>Blackbury,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rallinſon,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours obliged to love and ſerve you, whilſt <hi>Robert Rich.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Barb.</hi> 
                  <date>the 13 <hi>August,</hi> 1668.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>Sir, I have three ſeveral times of late appeared in the Aſſembly of the Quakers, where <hi>William Baily</hi> and his wife were chief in the Miniſtery. The occaſion that drew me thither, as alſo the entertainment amongſt them, I have thought meet here to inſert, that the wiſe in heart may judge how much contrary to the ſpirit of love and truth, they have appeared in all their dealings with me. The firſt time I came amongſt them was at <hi>William Plumlies,</hi> on the 4 of <hi>June,</hi> not having for a long time before been at any of their Meetings: and underſtanding that <hi>W. B.</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected amongſt them, (with whoſe Writings formerly I had great union) I was therefore now deſirous to ſee him, alſo to behold their order, and to know what manner of ſpirit moved upon the face of their deep. After he had ſpoken a long while, I took liberty to ſpeak a few words; the ſum of which was, That man lives not by words onely. For which <hi>W. B.</hi> condemned me as a babler, and told me that I made merry over the witneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His wife alſo accuſed me, ſaying I had blown a trumpet in printing my Letter, and that I had therein called a woman Whore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36451:8"/>did <hi>W. B.</hi> alſo revile me, alleadging that I had ordered thirty pounds to be given to the poor of their people, which he affirmed was not received by any of them; and that they denied both me and my gift, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which did fully manifeſt to me, that the ſpirit of pride, enmity, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and falſhood was amongſt them; which did occaſion the writing of this encloſed Letter, (as to <hi>W. B.</hi>) dated the 8 of <hi>June,</hi> which I delivered him with my own hand, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting an account of their words and actions; but have received not ſo much as one word in anſwer thereunto. Now whether they have done well, thus to condemn me for ſpeaking the truth, and for my gift of love to the poor of their people, I appeal to the witneſs of God in all men to judge.</p>
            <p>The ſecond time I went amongſt them, was at <hi>William Pearſe</hi> houſe on the 18 <hi>June,</hi> at which time I produced their Receipt under the hands of <hi>John Bolton, Amos Stod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dart,</hi> and <hi>Ger. Roberts,</hi> for the thirty pounds they received of you: by which it might appear that the ſaid money was by them received, with a clear intent to be diſpoſed of to the poor amongſt them, even as I had before declared to <hi>W. B.</hi> Which thing he could not then deny, when I had ſhewn the Receipt under the hands of thoſe perſons, though with much obſtinacie (and in the face of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) he had formerly aſſerted the contrary. Now as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the return of the money to my hand, (which they ſaid was then in the hands of <hi>Tho. Hart</hi> to repay unto me) I have this onely to offer to the honeſt and ſimple-hearted <hi>(viz)</hi> whether thoſe three perſons who ſay they received this money as from me, to beſtow amongſt their poor, and yet notwithſtanding decline their engagements in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution, will not onely render themſelves ill Stewards for their poor, but alſo juſtly fall under the imputation of the ſame deceit and falſhood which <hi>W. B.</hi> hath done, in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadging that they never received it from me to that end and purpoſe; yee upon this very ground onely (that the money was ſent to be returned me) <hi>W. B.</hi> and others of his diſciples (eſpecially <hi>John Tod,</hi> more bold and ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36451:8"/>then his fellows) would violently urge, and (by falſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning) defend and maintain <hi>W. B.</hi> in the truth, and me the onely lyer; whereas all that I ſaid was, that they had received money, and given their Receipt for the ſame; (both which <hi>W. B.</hi> formerly denied, and the Receipt then ſhewn fully proved.) And I never had ſo much as one word in controverſie with them about the return of the ſaid money, but always when they ſpake thereof, declared my readineſs to receive the ſame, as may appear in the Poſtſcript of my Letter to <hi>W. B.</hi> In which diſpute I did not onely ſee the Serpents ſubtilty, in turning and twining to ſave his head from being found the lyer, but alſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned the Scripture fulfilled upon them, which ſaith, <hi>Ye compaſs ſea and land to make one proſelyte, and when he is made, he is twofold more the childe of hell then themſelves,</hi> (or when they were one amongſt the Profane) not caring whom they ſlander, or what lyes they tell, ſo they may advance, ſtrengthen and increaſe their Party and Sect; whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit will the more fully appear by the following inſtance: for I lately ſpake with <hi>Tho. Hart,</hi> (ſince <hi>W. B.</hi> went off) and asked him whether he would pay me the thirty pounds which <hi>W. B.</hi> declared openly was in his hands for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: unto which <hi>T. H.</hi> made me anſwer, that in truth he had no ſuch money ſent him, nor had he order to pay the ſame; neither could he then inform me of any other perſon that would pay me that money. By all which it will evidently appear, that the ſpirit of deceit and falſhood is crept in and doth inhabit amongſt this people, and that the pretence of this money being remitted, (on which they grounded all their latter exaltations and accuſations) was in it ſelf a moſt eminent and notorious falſhood.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt time I came into their Aſſembly, was on the 25 of <hi>June,</hi> at <hi>William Marſhals.</hi> The cauſe of my coming then amongſt them, was to carry a printed paper written by <hi>William Baily,</hi> and intituled, <hi>A Testimony of Truth against all ſowers of diſſention, ſtrife and diſcord,</hi> &amp;c. in which Paper I perceived his ſpirit chiefly buſied in bitter exclamations againſt <hi>John Perrot,</hi> and all that owned him:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36451:9"/>in which Work I could ſee no other intent, then what <hi>G. F.</hi> had in writing (ſo bitterly, and contrary to truth) againſt <hi>J.P</hi>'s Book called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Amity, (viz.)</hi> then to ſow the ſeeds of enmity, ſtrife and falſhood, to make parties, and gather together ſuch as would aſſiſt him in the war againſt the Lamb. The conſideration of which, made me cry out within my ſelf, <hi>Oh how is the faithful citie become a harlot! in it was once the ſeat of judgement and righteouſneſs, but now oppreſſers and murtherers bear ſway and rule.</hi> For in truth, ſuch is the nature of his violent proceedings againſt <hi>John Perrot,</hi> proclaiming him worſe then <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying him with the opprobrious attributes of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Ranteriſm,</hi> &amp;c. yet hath not ſo much as manifeſted the leaſt evil <hi>J. P.</hi> hath ſaid or done, for which he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this his ſevere judgement and condemnation. In which practice of cruelty, I have conſidered <hi>W. B.</hi> as one ſtanding in the Serpentine ſubtilty of the Scribes and Phariſees, yea thoſe bloudy perſecutors of the Primitive times, who uſed to put the Chriſtians into Bears skins, that the dogs might tear them with the greater violence and fury. And whether this Paper (being written againſt a man that is dead, and not in a capacity of vindicating his own innocencie) hath not wrought the ſame effect upon thoſe that are one with <hi>W. B.</hi> I leave to the light of Right Reaſon in every man to judge. Certainly I have ſpoken with thoſe that have boldly cenſured <hi>J. P.</hi> for a wicked perſon, yet could render no other reaſon thereof, but that <hi>W. B.</hi> (of whoſe honeſty and integrity they had a very great eſteem) had ſo judged and condemned him. After long enquiry what the evil contents were of that Paper which <hi>J. P.</hi> is ſaid to have written, at length I was given to underſtand, that it was a Letter written to <hi>Jeane Stocks</hi> whilſt he was a priſoner in <hi>Rome;</hi> the purport of which diſcourſe is obedience to God in all things, though he ſhould (now) command what (once) he did to his ſervant<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſea.</hi> And becauſe formerly there hath been much ado in words and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting between <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi> concerning this Paper, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36451:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>other matters in difference betwixt them, which (though yet lie hid in ſecret) poſſibly may ſhortly come abroad to publick view, that the truth of things may be ſeen, and fully underſtood, whereat many have ſtumbled, yet know not at what; therefore ſhall ſay little more at preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that matter; onely that I have obſerved, that ſuch as <hi>J. P. J. N.</hi> &amp;c. eſpecially thoſe that forſake father and mother, (the Sect that nouriſhed and brought them forth) to follow the Lord fully and wholly, (as did <hi>Caleb, Joſhua,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 2.49. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9 34.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c.) not mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own reputation or fame, nor lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their lives unto the death; ſuch, I ſay, have been accounted in all ages, by this hypocritical, proud, ſelf-righteous generation, as the worſt of men, whom they call <hi>Ranters, Atheists, Blaſphemers, Devils,</hi> any thing, even all manner of evil, ſo they may wound the truth, and ſlay the innocent defenders thereof, whoſe harmleſs ſouls I ſee lying under the altar of truth, ſorely oppreſſed for their teſtimony thereunto, and crying out, <hi>How long, Lord God, holy and true, ere thou dost judge and revenge our bloud!</hi> For whoſe elect ſake, the God of my ſalvation will ſuddenly ariſe, and then behold enmity, lyes and falſhood <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (even all that one ſpirit of wickedneſs) will ſurely flie, hide it ſelf, and ſink again into the bottomleſs pit, from whence it came. <hi>Even ſo let all thine enemies periſh, O Lord God everlasting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At my firſt coming into this laſt meeting, <hi>W. B.</hi> (as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times) did much judge and condemn me in general terms. And when I was ready to depart, he called me, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Rich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; thou art a whoremonger, and hast an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous whoremongers ſpirit:</hi> and farther ſaid, <hi>Although I neither know, nor yet have heard any ſuch thing concerning thee, yet nevertheleſs I am aſſured it is truth, foraſmuch as I have not been deceived in others, in ſuch like caſes.</hi> To which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, judgement and condemnation of <hi>W. B.</hi> I ſay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven what himſelf ſaith in his Paper againſt <hi>J. P.</hi> (and I am perſwaded, with much more truth) <hi>viz.</hi> that the worſt of men (that ever I heard or read of) did never publiſh a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36451:10"/>more unjuſt and more unreaſonable then this: yea, the very Heathen, (that know not God) would ſurely bluſh to utter ſuch a judgement of condemnation againſt any man, without the leaſt knowledge or other proof of evil. And in caſe the Civil Magiſtrate ſhould follow this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>W. B.</hi> and take up ſuch a principle or way of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who is there (though never ſo innocent) that could be ſecure in life, limb, or eſtate? And if the Lord ſhould ſtir up and harden the hearts of Magiſtrates to deal with <hi>Quakers,</hi> as <hi>W. B.</hi> hath done by me, to judge and condemn them as the worſt of evil doers, without more proof or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence then evil ſurmiſe, or imagination onely; would it not be moſt juſt upon them? All which I return as their own money into their own ſacks, that they may ſee and conſider, how unlike the ſpirit of the <hi>Quakers</hi> is, to that which was in Chriſt Jeſus, who refuſed to interfere or med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the Magiſtrates work, whoſe kingdom is more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and of another nature then to have to do with ſuch carnal matters, though the greateſt evidence did appear that could be. (Read <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.3 to 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.13.) And Oh how bleſſed a thing it were, if all ſorts of men in their ſeveral ſtations, both as Magiſtrates and Miniſters, were true followers of Chriſt Jeſus in this particular! how would it eaſe and refreſh the whole creation, which groans under the unnatural yoke of that bondage which the hard impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of men have put upon them! Let therefore <hi>Caeſar</hi> have what properly belongs to him, <hi>viz.</hi> the right of rule and government in things Civil, in which (as good and wholeſom Laws ſhall direct) he may (and ought to be) a terrour to the evil doer, and a praiſe, honourer and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancer of them that do well. And let them that would be accounted the Miniſters of Chriſt, (under all ſorts of Profeſſions) not mingle with the Magiſtrates Rule and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, nor call for his aſſiſtance, (for that is Antichriſt, whoſe weapons are<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.36. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.55, 56. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6, 7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, &amp;c. <hi>Eph</hi> 6.12.</note> carnal in matters ſpiritual) but ſhew forth their works in the ſpirit of love, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, and patience, (the beſt and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36451:10"/>motives to convince the judgements and conſciences of men) and having freely received of the grace of God, let them freely give, and (not for filthy lucre) diſpenſe the ſame to others: knowing, that as neceſſity (in the Love) is laid upon them from the Lord, ſo their reward is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to them from him, for their continual ſupply and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, without any dependancie (either for honour or maintenance) upon ſecular Powers and Governments. But on the contrary, while the Civil Magiſtrate ſhall ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf ſo far ſubject to the commands of thoſe who (while they be eſteemed Miniſters of Chriſt) do yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding aim at worldly Eſtate and Preferment, yea Dominion and Supremacie over the Conſciences of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſhall (by their inſtigations) preſcribe, impoſe and enforce Rules of Worſhip in matters of Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; he doth herein not onely deveſt himſelf of that honour, peace and happineſs which God hath given him in worldly affairs, but alſo becomes a proſtitute to the end and ſervices of thoſe, who would uſe his power to no other end but (in promoting their own intereſt, honour, eaſe and plenty) to the vexation, grief and diſturbance of the reſt of Gods creation. Oh how greatly for many generations hath this one Beaſt, and this one Falſe Prophet riding him, diſturbed, vexed and curſed Gods creation! out of which Antichriſtian thraldom and abyſs of miſery, <hi>Good Lord deliver it. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what is written, you may ſee how this high and <hi>Luciferian</hi> people the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who for their ſhew and numbers have been as the Stars of heaven, and who for their pride and enmity are now caſt down; behold what <hi>clouds they are without water,</hi> even <hi>wandring ſtars, to whom is reſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever:</hi> whoſe fall is the riches of the world; inſomuch that carnal Whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Adulterers (over whom they have exalted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) ſhall ſooner repent, finde mercy, and enter Gods Kingdom of grace, then this ſpiritually adulterous proud generation, (that account ſo highly or themſelves, and to be the onely <hi>children of the kingdom</hi>) who ſhall be ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:36451:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>out. For though <hi>many</hi> of them have been <hi>called,</hi> yet but very <hi>few</hi> have been found that <hi>choſen generation,</hi> and <hi>Royal Priesthood,</hi> who offer up all their ſervices in the movings of the love of God, and who abide in that charity which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeth, nor knoweth, nor thinketh evil of another, (who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> judge and condemn themſelves) leaving all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the righteous judgement of God, who aſſuredly hath, doth, and will render to every man according to his work. So that the <hi>first</hi> in profeſſion are now become the <hi>last</hi> in poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, which ſtandeth not in words, nor yet in outward appearances, but in humility and love unfeigned, yea, in righteouſneſs, peace and joy,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>In which for ever we do ſit, and ſing</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eternal Hallelujahs to our King.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter written by <hi>Rob. Rich,</hi> to <hi>Will Baily</hi> and <hi>Mary Fiſher</hi> called thy wife; and to the rest of your hearers and followers, that ſo much judged and condemned <hi>R. R.</hi> in your General aſſembly held the <hi>4 June</hi> (which ye call the <hi>4</hi> Month) <hi>1668.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HErewith I preſent you the Receipt given under the hands of <hi>John Bolton, Amos Stoddart,</hi> and <hi>Gerrard Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts,</hi> for the thirty pounds received by them, as from me; which Receipt is expreſt in theſe words following.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="receipt">
               <body>
                  <p>Received 9th 11th Month called <hi>January 1667.</hi> of <hi>Jo. Rayns</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Merchant, the ſum of thirty pounds, by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36451:11"/>and appointment of <hi>Robert Rich</hi> of <hi>Barbadoes</hi> ſenior, which he ordered to be diſpiſed of to the poor amongst us. We ſay, Received by us</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Bolton, Amos Stoddart, Gerrard Roberts.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>That thou <hi>William Baily</hi> mayſt ſee and call to minde, how greatly ye reproached me for my love to you, and with what boldneſs and confidence you defended a moſt notorious evident falſhood, affirming with others in the face of a great Congregation, that the money was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by you, nor any whom ye owned for good Friends and Quakers, for that they all denyed both me and my gift: And notwithſtanding I told thee the names of thoſe perſons that had received the money, (whom thou didſt own then for good Friends) yet ſtill didſt aver, that thou wert ſure they never received any money (as from me) to diſtribute amongſt them: And if I had any ſuch Receipt, that it was or might be counterfeit and forged: adding, that thou hadſt ſpoken with thoſe friends ſince my Letter was out in Print, a little before thou lefteſt <hi>England;</hi> and wert ſure (as thou ſayeſt) that then they had not received it, neither would; and yet it doth appear by the Receipt to be received the 9th <hi>January,</hi> which was more then two months before. Which confident aſſertion of thine was alſo ſeconded with this ſolemn declaration, <hi>viz.</hi> that thou wouldſt diſown all ſuch, whoſoever they were, that ſhould receive money from me to ſuch an end, foraſmuch as long ſince I had been diſowned amongſt you. But what evil have I done in this thing? and were it not much more juſt and reaſonable, that they whom thou judgeſt, ſhould witneſs againſt thee, and diſown thee as an enemy to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, to truth, and to the poor amongſt you? So ſee what ſpirit acts you herein, and firſt learn to judge thy ſelf, before thou condemneſt the innocent.</p>
            <p>Now as touching the gift it ſelf, although thy wife did much reproach me, ſaying I had blown a Trumpet, in that I had printed my Letter, and had therein called the wife
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36451:12"/>of <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> Whore: alſo <hi>Tho. Rouſe</hi> the elder ſaid, he had known me do many mad actions, yet none ſo fooliſh as this, to give away ſo much money ſo vainly: and divers others of your proſelytes with the like or worſe imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which made me to cry out, ſaying, that <hi>many good works I had done amongst you,</hi> and asked <hi>for which of them it was that you did now ſtone me.</hi> All which I leave to the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God to judge between me and you concerning the truth of theſe things.</p>
            <p>And although Ignorance may have ſo far blinded your judgement, as to miſtake my charity; yet why your raſh preſumption or enmity ſhould lead you ſo far, as to make lyes your refuge, I know no reaſon, unleſs becauſe the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth is departed from you, and an evil ſpirit from the Lord is come upon you; and then I know you muſt act accordingly. As touching the receipt of the money by theſe three perſons, it is now verily believed by many of your own people, (to whom I have ſince ſhewed that Receipt) that the money is received by them, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt true and honeſt: which makes me to wonder at what <hi>Tho. Hart</hi> declared amongſt you, <hi>viz.</hi> that he had grounds to believe the money was received by friends, (as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them) but did alſo believe they were ſurpriſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And how they came to be trappann'd into ſo great a ſnare, as to give their Signal to a forgery, (as thou ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) I cannot imagine: but of this I am moſt certain, that it hath diſcovered a great deal of deceit and falſhood, yea a bitter, lying, and perſecuting proud ſpirit to inhabit your tents; which <hi>Babyloniſh garment</hi> hath long been ſeen to lie hid amongſt that tribe called the Miniſtry, the Teachers and Leaders of the Quakers; even ſuch ſpiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which if practiſed amongſt the <hi>Presbyterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,</hi> or others, (whom ye diſown, and can ſee in them nothing that is good) they would abhor themſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; which you as with a whores forehead boldly maintain and defend. You are, in truth, thoſe which juſtifie your ſelves before men; but God knoweth your hearts, and the day is at hand, even at your very door, which will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36451:12"/>reveal and preach, as upon the houſe-tops, many and great abominations, which yet lie hid amongſt you; that ſo you may be judged according to your deeds. In which day, all your ſmooth and gilded words of <hi>light</hi> and <hi>love</hi> will not hide you; neither yet your flouriſhing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and high eſteem you have of your ſelves, and the low eſteem you have of others, will not cover you from being ſeen. The <hi>golden head</hi> of that Image whereof others are the <hi>iron, lead</hi> and <hi>clay;</hi> yea, the very <hi>name</hi> in which ye have prayed and propheſied, (when innocent) and in which you have caſt out devils, and wrought wonders, ſhall now reject you, ſaying, <hi>Depart from me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Indeed, I have long ſeen <hi>the abomination that makes deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> ſtanding amongſt the Quakers, ever ſince that time, wherein <hi>G. F.</hi> did judge <hi>J. N.</hi> and invited his friends ſo to do, without ſhewing the leaſt reaſon or ground of his Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; even as thou thy ſelf haſt lately done in a printed paper writ againſt <hi>J. P.</hi> Wherefore <hi>hear the word of the Lord ye rulers of Sodom, and people of Gomorrha;</hi> 'tis this ſpirit that hath encompaſſed your <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> about as with Armies, and is now in bondage with her children; by which we know that the deſtruction thereof draweth nigh. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, 'tis that ſpirit of wickedneſs in the form of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that hath already torn your crown from off your head, and diſcovered your ſecret parts, ſo that the ſcab of contention and ſtrife is ſeen, which will never leave nor ceaſe to divide you, till the name of <hi>Quaker</hi> become a hiſs and a ſcorn amongſt the Nations. <hi>And you ſhall leave your name for a curſe to my choſen,</hi> (whom you have curſed) <hi>ſaith the Lord God everlasting, who will ſlay thee, and call his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants by another name,</hi> (it may be <hi>Hallelujah</hi>) which you have ſo much defam'd.)</p>
            <p>And you that (for the vaſt numbers of your Tribes) have ſeemed to magnifie your ſelves in your increaſe of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; Wo be to you that now give ſuck, (and take ſo much pains to adde to your Sect) for behold, in one day loſs of children and widowhood ſhall come upon you: yea, a voice (as that in <hi>Ramah</hi>) ſhall be heard among you, lamenting
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36451:13"/>your children becauſe they are not. Thus am I clear from the bloud of all men, in that I have not ceaſed both by words and writing to forewarn of the coming of this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who for more then ten years laſt paſt have been that poor Aſs ſpeaking as with mans voice, reproving and withſtanding the madneſs of this ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wrathful, bitter, perſecuting ſpirit; knowing right well when it entred, and you thereby came to reject the Lord, that he ſhould not reign over you by his Spirit of light and love, but rather choſe to your ſelves a King, like unto other Sects and Nations, for to judge and rule you; who was not the Unction, nor the Anointed of the Lord; nor yet the Olive, Fig, nor Vine, that could heal, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, or binde you up; but the<note n="*" place="margin">Read <hi>Judg.</hi> 9th and <hi>Rev.</hi> 9th chap.</note> Bramble, and King of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pit, that ſhall ſo rend, tear and devour you, till not one ſtone ſhall be left upon another, (which thing tell <hi>G. F.</hi> that FOX your King.) Alas! what are all your ſmoothe words of light, love and truth, whilſt they ſpring from the root and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Falſhood, envie and bitterneſs? And what is it to ſpeak with the tongue of men and angels, to have the gift of prophecie, to open myſteries, or to have all faith that could remove mountains, and have not love and charity, what will all this avail you? Are you better herein then <hi>Balaam</hi> was? I tell you nay: for he knew as much as you do, and was more honeſt and ſincere; for he knew not onely the difference between the two ſeeds, (when his eyes were opened) which was bleſſed, and which accurſed; but was alſo well acquainted with the ſeed of God, its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, progreſs and end; yea, and more, he (did not curſe it, but) owned it, and would ſpeak nothing but truth; and what the Lord put in his mouth, that onely would he ſay; but ye utter lyes and falſhood with great confidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the innocent, even what the devil ſuggeſteth. Thus having loſt your firſt love, and forſaken the faith once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints; you are now like that evil ſpirit caſt out, running to and fro, walking through the dry places
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36451:13"/>of your Elders traditions, following the footſteps of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek</hi> the firſt of Nations, thoſe you call <hi>Good old Friends,</hi> ſeeking reſt, but never ſhall finde any, ſo long as <hi>Balak</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> that bitter ſpirit, leads to curſe whom God will ſurely bleſs, and bring over you; for ye muſt fall, and (with <hi>Haman, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi>) be enſnared and taken, even in the ſame pit of cruel deceit, which you have dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for your innocent brethren: and herein (for ſome time) will the faith and patience of the Saints be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</p>
            <p>You greatly cry out and call upon others to fear and dread the Lord, yet your ſelves are ſo ignorant of that Leſſon, that ye blindly run on to judge the innocent, and condemn the truth; yea, to ſmite the apple of Gods eye, and irreverently reach at the Signet on his right hand, by condemning and ſpeaking evil of the things you know not; which doth ſufficiently demonſtrate, that you are out of the pure fear, that keeps the heart clean from thoſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations into which you ſo eaſily run. For my part, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though my ſpirit is oftentimes ſeized with a powerful, ſweet, and awful enjoyment of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, yet) I am not<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 6.</note> afraid of him (as when I was one with you) for I have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſpirit of bondage again to fear; but the ſpirit of peace and love, in which I receive him as a Father, rejoycing at his approaches, and do not fear him as an enemy, that would take advantage againſt me. I do well know the difference between the ſeed of the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, and the free workings of grace; and what it is to act towards God for fear of his wrath, plagues and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (which thou threatneſt my death bed withal) and what it is to do the will of my Father as my meat and drink: and long have I known a difference between the firſt and ſecond Covenant, betwixt thoſe that think they can keep themſelves in the light and love of God, (which <hi>Peter</hi> preſumed, as ye do; but fell moſt notoriouſly, as ye have) and thoſe that feel the Lord their Shepherd, and depend onely upon him for their daily food and ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36451:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>who rightly ſee their own weakneſs, and can deny themſelves, as not being able to watch one hour, neither preſerve themſelves one minute in the love and favour of God: theſe, and ſuch as theſe, being horn again of the innocent ſeed of love, and that abiding in them, (and not taken away from them, as it was from<note n="*" place="margin">Read 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.15. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3 &amp; 9.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi>) preſerveth from ſin, and from falling away. Alſo I have knowns diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of condemnation, which indeed is glorious; but there is a ſtate of jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that exceeds in glory: under the former is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> at the foot whereof I have formerly ſeen the Quakers and their Leaders, ſtanding with <hi>Moſes</hi> after the fleſh, filled with fear and trembling from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord; which was a glorious adminiſtration: but the later ſhews forth Mount <hi>Sion</hi> with its inhabitants, even the whole number of One hundred fourty and four thouſand; thoſe faithful, choſen and ſealed ones, who ſtand before the Lord in his preſence, rejoycing, and (without fear) ſinging the ſong of <hi>M ſes</hi> and the Lamb, <hi>Hallelujahs;</hi> who witneſs full redemption by his bloud, life and ſpirit, out of all evil Kindreds, Nations, Tongues and People: children that cannot lye, neither faiſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and perſecute the innocent. In the firſt, the heirs dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer nothing from ſervants, though lords of all, while they lie under the hard impoſition of tutors and governours, ſuch as thou thy ſelf art, which enjoyn to dread and fear the Lord, to watch, and to keep to the light: a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> your ſelves are out of; elſe why were ye ſo angry with me, for ſaying the Lord was my keeper? You are thoſe that binde heavie burthens upon others, which in the leaſt you will not bear your ſelves. Neither will ye judge, condemn and deny your ſelves, that you might ſo enter the kingdom of grace; nor yet ſuffer others, that would, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o enter, who are poor and naked, hungry and thirſty, without money or deſert. But the ſecond Covenant ſpeaketh otherwiſe, (<note n="*" place="margin">Read <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.37 <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17</note> 
               <hi>Ho, every one that will, let him come</hi>) and is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36451:14"/>upon better promiſes. He that knoweth the Spirits meaning, let him read <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10, 11. and 59.21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.33. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3, &amp;c. to the 8. and hath a more ſure foundation then mans ſelf-righteouſneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> the eternal Word of grace, faith, and love ſhed abroad in our hearts, the ſeal of our ſonſhip; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſt Jeſus in us, our joy, our crown and glory, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the full aſſurance of that perfect love which caſteth out fear: and thoſe that are here, will need no other tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor nor teacher, ſave Love onely; and having paſſed from the voice of that trumpet, and ſound of words, under which ye are held, whether that of the letters teaching, or that of mans preaching; let <hi>Sinai</hi> therefore quake, and the earth be removed, let the mountains melt at his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, yet we will not fear: for God is in the midſt of us as a King, and mighty man of arms, that teacheth our hands to war, and our fingers to fight; the terrour of whoſe preſence is our comfort and preſervation. Let the hypocrites in <hi>Sion</hi> fear and he afraid: we are not come to that mountain that might not be touched, where horror, fear and trembling is felt; but to the mountain of Gods love and free grace, the <hi>new Jeruſalem,</hi> and Citie of joy, peace and reſt, whoſe walls are ſalvation, and whoſe gates are made of praiſes and Hallelujahs; yea, to God the Judge of all, and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect: and this I clearly ſee to be a ſtate, diſpenſation, and a kingdom yet to come with thee, and many more who are ſo hotly contending for the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſtriving about ſome carnal fleſhly appearance, ſome bodily exerciſe, or outward obſervation, that profiteth not: and while you are buſied about theſe things, the evil is ſtill over your hearts, and the great and weighty matters of the Law neglected: inſomuch that the power of love, which leads into peace, unity and amity with God, and all that is good in his creation, ye are ſtrang rs unto. And all your meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, worſhips and ſervices, all your holineſs, knowledge, and righteouſneſs, being void of charity, (and your hands full of the bloud of the innocent) what is it all worth?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36451:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>is it better then the cutting off a dogs neck, or ſlaying of a man?</p>
            <p>By all this that hath been ſpoken, 'tis evident in what ſtate you at preſent ſtand, and that there is much more attainable, which you are yet ignorant of: for there are three eſtates or ſtages, by which God doth lead his people into peace and reſt, beſides the ſtate of the Heathen that know not God; notwithſtanding he in them lives, moves, and is their being, <hi>viz. Sinai</hi> and the Law, <hi>Golgotha</hi> and the Croſs, <hi>Jeruſalem above</hi> and the crown.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, you have been and ſtill are exerciſed under fear, dread and horrour, being bound to ſtrict obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thereby working out your ſalvation with fear and trembling; all which the Son of man alſo fulfilled in the days of his fleſh, as being born under the Law, and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience by the things he ſuffered: and thus far you ſtand with him in your earthly teſtimony.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is a ſtate of death, (into which as yet you are not baptized) not having learned to<note n="*" place="margin">Read <hi>Mark</hi> 10.18, 21, 22. <hi>Joh</hi> 5.30 &amp; 8. &amp; 28. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2, 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3, 4, 5.</note> deny and condemn your ſelves, nor are you ceaſed from all your own works as he did from his; not crucified with Chriſt, nor dead with the Lord, which is more then to put off the body of ſin, or to account our own righteouſneſs as filthy and menſtruous; but even the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie and righteouſneſs of the Son, the ſeed of the promiſe muſt be offered up, and nayled to the Croſs, for this onely God accepteth, and in whom he is always well pleaſed. (Read <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3, 13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14, 16, &amp;c. and 4.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15.) This mediation or middle ſtate (may truely be called <hi>Purgatory,</hi> or <hi>Limbo Patrum</hi>) through which (ſelf-denial, and following Chriſt in us) all that attain to bleſſedneſs muſt needs enter and paſs: ſo they come to receive the better reſurrection. (Read <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21, 29. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35.) This death, ſelf-denial and purgation, but very few amongſt you can witneſs, who while ye exalt your ſelves in your outward
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36451:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>carnal priviledges, and the blameleſneſs of your Legal righteouſneſs, cannot<note n="*" place="margin">Read <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.20, 22. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3 to the 11.</note> reſigne into death, and account all your excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie as loſs and dung in compariſon of the Spirit of Free grace, and the leadings thereof. Neither have I ſeen many amongſt you (beſides <hi>J. N.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi>) who by their fellowſhip with Chriſt in his death have denied themſelves, and made themſelves of no reputation, that ſo they might obtain the beſt reſurrection amongſt their innocent brethren, whom ye have ſlain, and buried (as ye did them) under great reproach and ſhame, for their ſubjection and obedience to the Father of lights and ſpirits; which reſurrection having attained, they ſhall receive a name better then that of ſons and daughters. Thus the firſt are become the laſt, and the laſt the firſt. Go humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God, that in due time he may exalt you into the number of that Name (of love, the higheſt power) to which every knee muſt bow.</p>
            <p>The third, laſt, and moſt excellent eſtate, is to be riſen with Chriſt Jeſus, and to ſit down in the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> with him in the heavenly places, the everlaſting Sabbath of reſt, which is a kingdom that cannot be ſhaken, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the heavens; the which remains, when the old paſſeth away; a fixt and ſure habitation, whoſe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants are ever ſinging praiſes, and drinking new wine in the Fathers kingdom, where all old things are paſſed away, and all things anew brautified with the Spirits leading, and nothing repreſented in the oldneſs of the letter. And ſuch a people there are in this preſent world, even as he is in heaven. (Read and underſtand <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. and 15.48 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. and 6.16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3 and 2.6. and 14. and 16.4 24. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. and 3.1 <hi>Heb.</hi> 2 11. and 12.22, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4 17.) Behold, we ſhut not our gates at all by day (fearing no ſpirituals) nor have we any night (as the Prophets had) for the Lord God is riſen in us, a ſhield, and a ſun which no more go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down; for Chriſt being once dead, and riſen again,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36451:16"/>dies no more, but leads captivity captive, giving up all to the free grace and leadings of the Father, where death and hell is ſwallowed up in victory, that the eternal principle of love may be all in all. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi> Go ye, and learn what this meaneth; then will you come to ſee, that to be a Chriſtian indeed is a very high calling, not made by a carnal commandment, nor outward obſervation, writ, or ceremony of mans inſtitution whatſoever; no, not by the waſhing away of the filth of the fleſh, nor yet by breaking of carnal bread: nothing leſs makes a Chriſtian, then the power of an endleſs life, the bread from heaven, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling of Gods moſt bleſſed ſpirit of grace, his Son, in whom <hi>Abraham, Mary,</hi> and all the faithful in every Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sect and People are bleſſed. Read <hi>Gen.</hi> 22 3. <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10. &amp; 72 27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Luk</hi> 1.42, 48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 9, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 9, 16.) creating in them new hearts, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting the anſwer of a pure conſcience towards God, in a vertuous life, and innocent, harmleſs, loving converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards men (as well to a foe, as to a friend; and to the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.39.44, 45. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.35, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.18.</note> evil, as to the good) this principle of Love (onely) is that which makes a true Chriſtian; and he that hath not this Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus in him abiding, to rule and guide, is but a meer Heathen, yea a Reprobate to every good work. (Read, and underſtand <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13 5. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2 6.) For except Chriſt Jeſus, that Spirit, work all our works in us and for us; nothing we do without him, will finde acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation with God the Father: no, though we give our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be burnt, and all our goods to ſeed the poor, from a ſpirit of ſelf-endedneſs, to exalt, gratifie, or pleaſe our ſelves or others, (not having in us love and charity, the onely begotten of the Father, and expreſs image of his perſon) all is nothing. And doubtleſs many Heathens, and Roman-like ſpirits, have and may ſuffer from a wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful principle, (as ſome preach Chriſt of envie, and for to defend their own Way and Worſhip) with as much bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, zeal and reſolution, as ye can do. Wherefore look
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36451:16"/>to the root that leads you either to do or to ſuffer, and earneſtly pray and ſeek for that beſt and moſt excellent love and charity, that you may have enough thereof to ſerve in the time of need, and to carry you thorow that wilderneſs and ſore famine which is ſeen coming upon you and all fleſh: that if it be the will of God you muſt ſuffer, you may ſo do as Chriſtians, (with joy and patience) for well doing, and not as buſie-bodies in other mens matters, nor yet as ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor falſe accuſers of the innocent, neither as deſpiſers and revilers of others more juſt and righteous then your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Had you been baptized with this ſpirit of love that thinks none ill, you would not have ſo much condemned me for an innocent word, for calling (as <hi>Geo: Forſter</hi> ſaid) one of my friends by way of ſalute (long ſince at the Bridge) <hi>Raſcal;</hi> at which he took no offence, neither would <hi>G. F.</hi> have done, had not he looked out with an evil eye. For 'tis a word I dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe to ſucking children, &amp; am not convinced of the leaſt evil therein: nor would I have you ignorant, how that words and works are either good or bad from the principle or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from whence they flow and proceed. He that from the root of<note n="*" place="margin">Read <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.20, 22. &amp; 12.34. and 18.9. with 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3 5. <hi>Hoſ</hi> 1 2.</note> enmity ſpeaks a word againſt his brother (mark) is a manſlayer, yea a murtherer, and is in danger of hell-fire. Whereas <hi>Abraham</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to ſlay his innocent and onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſon, from a principle of love and obedience, had a great recompence of reward. Wherefore look to the root and principle that leads you; firſt make the tree good. For after this manner is the ax now laid to the root of every rotten heart, which will hew and cut you down (ye <hi>whited walls,</hi> ye <hi>painted ſepulchres</hi>) who thus <hi>make a man an offender for a word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when you had for a long time judged and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me as one guilty of all manner of evil in general, but proving not ſo much as one particular; indeed accuſing me of many things, as being a proud perſon, a wine-bibber, and a friend of publike ſinners; things wherein the witneſs of God did not at all condemn me: which made me cry out,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36451:17"/>that it was a ſmall matter for me to be judged by man in thoſe things wherein I was juſtified of the Lord. Thus your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers having called the good man of the houſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 3.30. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.38, 39</note> (<hi>viz.</hi> the Spirits leading) <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> it matters not what you call them of his houſhold. You are indeed thoſe that judge according to outward appearance: but I judge no man ſo, neither in meat, drink, nor apparel. For I am ſatisfied, that one man may be much prouder in Sackcloth, then another that weareth Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet and Sattin: and I know every creature of God to be good, being received with humility and thankſgiving. Which made me again cry out, ſaying, Judge your ſelves, condemn your ſelves, who ſo eaſily can ſee and eſpie out a moat in anothers eye, but not the beam in your own. This counſel alſo ye rejected againſt your ſelves, calling it deceit and a lye; which made me to ſay this Scripture was alſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in your ears, which ſaith, The time ſhall come, that they will not endure ſound doctrine. And why were ye ſo angry with me for ſaying, that man did not live by words onely, but by the Word of grace and love ſhed abroad in our hearts, the bread of life, which ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtains the ſoul in peace and reſt? This likewiſe ye called deceipt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and denied my voice therein: after which I called you friends; at the which you were exceeding wroth, crying out againſt my deceit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and asking me how I could call you friends. To when I replied, that in truth I had unitie with thoſe that could love their enemies, as with him that called <hi>Judas</hi> friend. Thus I return you theſe things, as your own money into your own ſacks, that you may ſee and conſider what manner of ſpirit it is which leadeth you into theſe and ſuch-like ways and practices: and till I hear of thy and your publick repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as you have publickly appeared againſt the truth, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent defenders thereof, I ſhall eſteem you no better then <hi>Judas,</hi> or as infi els and heathens, that have denied the truth and faith once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints; which to maintain, ſome have hazarded the loſs of all things, yea ſuffe ed great ſhame and reproach amongſt you. But bleſſed be God, that which ye intended for evil againſt me, that hath the Lord my God turned unto good: for which my ſoul doth bleſs and magnifie his Name, and for ever give thanks, even whilſt I am, and when I am no more</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robert Rich.</signed>
               <date>8 <hi>June</hi> 1668.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am told by ſome of your peope (to whom I have ſhewed the Receipt) that the <hi>30</hi>
               <abbr>l.</abbr> received by you from me is again returned, but thou ſayst it never was received at all; and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſay, If it be not returned, it ſhall be. Thus is Babel built amongſt you, and the citie of the Quakers become confuſion. For my part, if it be not received kept, and diſtributed amongſt the poor of your people, in and by the ſame ſpirit of ſaving kindneſs I gave it, &amp; that you think good to return it to me; I ſhall not refuſe to receive it again; and not doubt of finding thoſe, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e worthy then your ſelves (though in the highways and hedges, ſcratcht, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and caſt out by you) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> kindneſs will accept, receive, and make uſe of the ſame, &amp; not ſo reproachfully deſpiſe me for my love as you have done.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
